（親衛隊）
第二バレラスからの迎撃終了。
Attack from Second Baleras complete.
（森雪）何をなさったのです？
What did you do?
（デスラー）ちょっとした思いつきでね
波動エネルギーを→
Just an idea... I used the Wave Motion Energy as a weapon.
武器に応用してみたのだ。
The Wave Motion Gun?
波動砲…。
（親衛隊）ヤマト　消滅したもよう！
The Yamato appears to have been destroyed.
あっ！
（デスラー）苦難の果て→
Send observation data. After a long, hard journey, they died right before their goal.
目的地を目の前に散る。
What a beautiful ending.
なかなか　美しい最期じゃないか。
あぁ…。
（ノラン）あっ。
（デスラー）艦長は
どんな男だったのだろうね。→
I wonder what the captain was like.
I'd love to have met him, to give him a word of appreciation.
会って　ねぎらいの言葉の一つも→
掛けてやりたかった。
んん…。
（デスラー）ユリーシャ姫は
気分が　すぐれないようだ。→
Princess Yurisha seems unwell. Take her outside.
外へ　お連れしたまえ。
（ノラン）参りましょう。
Let's go.
ピピッ（警告音）
（親衛隊）着弾点付近に艦影。→
Something on radar, near point of impact... The Yamato.
ヤマトです！
あっ！
AA guns are badly damaged!
（南部）対空砲座　損害　大きい！
（太田）センサー群に　障害発生！
Sensors aren't working right!
（百合亜）惑星　崩壊していきます。
The planet's collapsing.
（メルダ）エピドラが…。
Epidra is no more...
A single attack, capable of destroying a planet...
（古代進）
星を　死に至らせる一撃。
It's the Wave Motion Gun.
（沖田十三）波動砲だ。
えっ？
I'm seeing fluctuations in the gravitational gradient.
（真田）重力勾配の変動が
検出されている。→
This waveform is definitely that of the Wave Motion Gun.
この波形は
波動砲に間違いないでしょう。
We will continue to the inner system.
本艦は
このまま　内惑星系に突入する。
（島・古代）えっ？
波動砲といえど→
Even the Wave Motion Gun has difficulty targeting objects at sub-light speeds.
亜光速の物体を
狙撃するのは困難だ。
敵の懐深く入らぬかぎり
活路は見いだせない。
Without going deep into their range, we have no way to win.
Full speed ahead! Our destination is Garmillas.
最大戦速。　目標　ガミラス！
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ウィン　ウィン…（警告音）
（親衛隊）ヤマト　亜光速で接近中！
The Yamato is approaching at sub-light speeds!
Interesting.
（デスラー）面白い。
（親衛隊）第二バレラスの→
Minister Talan from Second Baleras.
タラン長官です。
（タラン）総統
今の砲撃で　システムの一部に→
My lord, the attack damaged parts of our systems.
障害が発生しました。
修復を急がせたまえ。
Have repairs completed as soon as possible.
お言葉ですが　亜光速の目標を→
But targeting an object at sub-light speed with the Desler cannon is difficult.
デスラー砲で捕捉するのは
困難です。
It will slow down in a moment.
じきに　速度を落とすだろう。
（親衛隊）総統→
My lord, Her Highness Starsha is on the hotline.
スターシャ猊下から
ホットラインが入っております。→
直接　総統と…。
ピピピッ（受信音）
She wishes to speak to you directly.
What are you doing, Lord Desler?
（スターシャ）デスラー総統
一体　どういうおつもりです？→
Using Wave Motion Energy as a weapon is sheer madness.
波動エネルギーを兵器に使うなど
正気の沙汰とは思えません。
Are you here to complain?
抗議かね？
そうです。
Yes.
抗議　抗議…
君が　ここを訪れるときは→
Complaints, complaints. Every time you come here, it's to complain.
いつも　抗議ばかりだ。→
Then why do you not complain to the Terrons?
ならば　あのテロン人たちにも→
抗議をしてはどうかね？
どういうこと？
What do you mean?
The ship you brought here uses Wave Motion Energy as a weapon, as well.
（デスラー）
君が呼び寄せた　あの艦もまた→
波動エネルギーを
兵器に転用している。
Impossible...
そんな…。
そういえば→
Come to think of it, you saw that your little sister is doing well, yes?
妹君の元気な姿
君も　見てくれただろうね？
はっ…。
私が命じて　保護させたのだ。
I ordered her kept safe.
What are you thinking, Abelt?
何を考えているの？　アベルト。
I'm doing this for you.
（デスラー）
君のために　やっているのだ。
Stop it.
やめて…。
（デスラー）スターシャ。
Starsha...
お願い。
Please!
そうか…　残念だよ。
I see. How unfortunate.
Stop this, Abelt.
（スターシャ）もうやめて　アベルト…。
（百合亜）１０時に艦影。　空母３！
Ships at ten o'clock. Three carriers!
（真田）波動防壁　展開。
まだだ。
Deploy the Wave Motion Shields.
No, not yet.
まだ早い。
はい。
Yes, sir.
Half speed... Launch the Hayabusas!
両舷　半速。　ハヤブサを降ろせ。
The front carrier fleet will soon encounter the enemy.
（オペレーター）
前衛空母艦隊　間もなく　会敵。
Attack.
（ギムレー）仕掛けなさい。
メランカ　発進させろ。
Launch the Melancas!
Don't let them near the Yamato! Shoot them down!
（加藤）ヤマトに近づけるな！
たたき落とせ！
Hard to starboard. We're heading straight for Garmillas!
面舵いっぱい。
このまま　ガミラス星へ突入せよ。
ビシュン！
バシュー　バシュー　バシュー！
ドドォーン！
ダダダダッ！
ドーン！
ピュン　ピュン　ピュン　ピュン…
バシュー！
ドーン！
ドーン！　ドーン！
ドォーン！
（玲）ふふっ。
（オペレーター）前衛艦隊　空母に損害。
（オペレーター）ヤマト　依然　降下中。
Damage to the forward carrier fleet!
The Yamato is still descending.
Protecting the new capital is our only goal.
（ギムレー）守るべきは　新しき都。
But nonetheless, we must make a show of this.
しかし　ポーズは付けなくてはね。
（メルダ）ここが　帝都バレラス。
このルートを突破すれば→
This is the Imperial Capitol City of Baleras.
Make it through here, and you'll be at the palace.
総統府に　肉薄できる。
うむ。　本艦は　これより→
Very well... We will now strike at the enemy's heart, Lord Desler's palace!
敵中枢　デスラー総統府をつく。
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ウウゥーー！（警報）
We've allowed the enemy onto our own soil?
（ヒス）
本土に　敵の侵入を許すとは…。→
What is the Imperial Guard doing?
親衛隊は　何をしている!?
Gimleh... He's useless!
（セレステラ）ギムレー
役に立たないヤツ！
ピシュン　ピシュン…
ドォーン！
ビシュン！
ガン！
ドォーン！
ビシュン！
Deploy the Wave Motion Shields!
波動防壁　展開。
ドォーン！
We're going to ram the palace!
このまま　総統府に突入する！
Brace for impact!
衝撃に備えよ！
きゃあ！
（ノラン）あっ！
（一同）うぅ…。
んん…　あっ…。
みんな　大丈夫か？
総員　武器を携帯。
Is everyone all right?
Everyone, equip weapons. Assemble a team and take command, Kodai!
古代　突入隊を編制。　指揮を執れ。
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ウウゥーー！
Let's get out of here.
ここから逃げましょう。
うん。
Yeah.
あっ　あぁ…。　あっ！
I thought you'd say that.
そう言ってくれると思った。
（一同）うぅ…。
（親衛隊）被害状況　知らせ！
Impossible...
（ヒス）バカな！
（セレステラ）総統は　ご無事か!?→
Is our lord safe?
すぐ　所在を確認なさい！
（ガデル）落ち着け。
Find him now!
Calm down...
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）デウスーラの
分離シークエンスを起動します。
Initiating Deusura decoupling sequence.
The Deusura?
（ヒス）デウスーラ？
（セレステラ）あっ　どいて！
Out of the way!
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）８　７　６→
５　４　３→
２　１　０！
It's accelerating...
加速している。
Something has launched from the palace!
（百合亜）
総統府から　離脱する物体あり。
I can feel it.
（ユリーシャ）感じる。
あっ。
Yuki is aboard it.
（ユリーシャ）雪が乗っている。
No... You left me behind?
（セレステラ）
そんな　私を置いて…。　うそよ。→
This can't be... This can't be!
うそよ～～!!
My lord, Second Baleras will be under our control shortly.
（レクター）総統
第二バレラスのコントロールは→
間もなく　掌握できます。
As planned.
（デスラー）予定どおりだな。
（レクター）はい。
Yes.
（デスラー）これより　作戦行動に移る！
（レクター）ザー・ベルク！
We shall now begin the operation.
Zar Belk.
Dimensional Mobile City Fortress Second Baleras
Minister Talan, the central control system
is being taken over from outside!
（オペレーター）タラン長官
中央コントロールシステムが→
Minister Talan, the central control system
is being taken over from outside!
外部から強制介入を受けています。
（タラン）特定しろ。
Find the origin.
これは…
デウスーラからのコマンドです。
The... The command is coming from the Deusura.
Our leader...
（タラン）総統が？
タラン長官→
Minister Talan, Industrial Sector 633 is entering decoupling sequence.
６３３工区が
分離シークエンスに入ります！
バ…　バカな…。
Impossible...
Why don't you go?
（ユリーシャ）なぜ行かないの？
なぜ　雪を助けに行かないの？
Why don't you go save Yuki?
突入隊を指揮します。
（ユリーシャ）古代！
I'll command the assault team.
Kodai!
（百合亜）レーダー　感あり。
拡大投影。
Something on radar!
Magnify!
A massive object in orbit!
（百合亜）軌道上に　巨大構造物！
（ＡＵ０９）
推定質量　６０００万トン。→
Estimated mass, 60,000,000 tons. Descending from Lagrange point L1.
ラグランジュポイントＬ１カラ
降下シテキマス。→
Estimated impact point is the palace. In other words, here.
推定落着ポイントハ　総統府。
ツマリ　ココデス。
（オペレーター）依然　降下中。
It continues to descend.
The decoupling command came from Lord Desler!
（オペレーター）分離コマンドは
デスラー総統からのものです。
From our lord?
（ガデル）総統が!?
（オペレーター）地表到達まで→
It will reach point of impact at 2400 gek.
あと２４００ゲック。
（ヒス）なんと愚かな…。→
How foolish...
総員退去！
帝都全域に　緊急事態宣言！
Everyone, evacuate! Declare an emergency in the capital!
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ウウゥーー！
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）緊急事態！→
This is an emergency! Evacuate the palace at once!
全職員は
速やかに　総統府より退去せよ！
（ヒルデ）えっ？　えっ？　ああっ！
I repeat... This is an emergency! Evacuate the palace at once!
Staying here is dangerous.
ここにいては危険だ。
これが…
これが指導者のすることか？
Is this... Is this how a leader behaves, Desler?
デスラー!!
（親衛隊）誘導ビーコン　キャッチ。
Guidance beacon, locked.
（親衛隊）ドッキング　完了。
（親衛隊）デスラー砲との回路接続。
Docking complete. Connected to Desler Cannon circuit.
（レクター）タラン長官です。
Minister Talan is here.
My lord, please tell me your intention!
（タラン）総統　どうか
真意を　お聞かせください。→
なぜ　６３３工区を
バレラスに落とすのです!?→
Why are you dropping Industrial Sector 633 on Baleras?
あなたは…。
（デスラー）これは　通過儀礼なのだ。
This is a rite of passage.
A rite of passage?
通過儀礼？
（デスラー）ヤマトと共に→
Baleras and the Yamato will be annihilated together.
バレラスは消滅する。
ガミラスは
その尊い犠牲をもって→
And this noble sacrifice will give rise to the rebirth of Garmillas.
古き衣を　脱ぎ捨てる。
（デスラー）
作戦終了後　第二バレラスは→
After the operation, Second Baleras will land on Iscandar.
イスカンダルへ降り立つ。→
I hereby declare this orbital city fortress to be the new capital of Garmillas.
私は　ここに宣言する！→
今　この瞬間より
この機動都市要塞こそが→
ガミラスの新たなる帝都
新たなる中心→
A new center! A new Baleras!
（通信）
新たなるバレラスであると！
んん～　すばらしい。
Splendid.
And this Second Baleras will be a bridge between Iscandar and Garmillas.
（デスラー）そして　この第二バレラスが
イスカンダルとガミラスの→
懸け橋となるのだ！
Twenty minutes until impact.
（ＡＵ０９）
構造物ノ落着マデ　アト２０分。
波動砲　発射準備。
Prepare to fire the Wave Motion Gun.
えっ!?
沖田…。
Okita...
バレラスに落下する質量を
破壊できるのは→
Only the Wave Motion Gun could destroy that much mass.
波動砲をおいて　ほかにない。
あっ。
（ユリーシャ）「言葉ではなく→
Through actions... Not words.
その行動で」。
（ユリーシャ）
今は　誰もが最善を尽くすとき。
This is the time for everyone to do their best.
What you must do... What only you can do!
自分がすべきことを…
自分にしかできないことを。
That's why I'm going after Yuki...
だから　私が雪を…。
ダメだ！
No!
That is what I must do.
それは　俺がすべきことだ。
Captain, give me permission to launch in a Zero.
艦長　自分に
ゼロでの出撃許可を下さい。
古代　現時点をもって
君の戦術長としての任を解く。
Kodai, you are relieved of your duties as Tactical Officer.
別命！　古代一尉は　これより→
You have another mission... To rescue Operations Officer Mori.
森船務長救出の任に就け！
Yes, sir!
はい！
んん…。
ふふっ。
その際　同行者１名を認める。
I will allow you to take one person.
えっ？
（ユリーシャ）ありがとう！　ふふっ。
Thank you!
古代進
森船務長救出の任に就きます。
I, Susumu Kodai, will now go to rescue Operations Officer Mori.
I've got this. In exchange...
（南部）こっちは任せろ。
そのかわり→
Bring her back.
彼女を頼む。
うん。
（徳川）うん　うん。
≫シューン（ドアの音）
（メルダ）ふふっ…。
（島）えっ？
ビィー　ビィー　ビィー…（警告音）
くっ！
ピュン　ピュン
ドォーン！
メルダ！
（メルダ）ユリーシャ様を→
Melda...
I'm simply protecting Lady Yurisha.
お守りしただけだ。
ビシュー！　ビシュー！
ドォーン！
ピュン　ピュン　ピュン　ピュン…
ダダダダッ！
ドォーン！
（メルダ）あっ！
（玲）私に任せてください。
Leave this to me.
To us.
（メルダ）「私たちに」だ。
みんな…。
Everyone...
You should do what only you can do.
（加藤）お前は
お前にしかできないことをやれ。
古代。
ああ…。　ああ！
Kodai...
Yeah... Yeah!
Take care of the princess!
（加藤）姫に　よろしくな。
I'm serious.
（玲）ほんと…　ですよ。
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）
コアシップとの接続確認の後→
After linking with the core ship, Company 6 is to load the Deusura ll.
第６中隊は　デウスーラⅡ世の→
弾糧搬入を開始。
（作業兵）補給準備　急がせろよ。
Get that resupply ready!
ここが制御室ね。
This is the control room.
（ノラン）
脱出するんじゃないんですか？
Aren't we escaping?
The enemy was using the Wave Motion Gun.
敵は　波動砲を持っていた。
このままじゃ　ヤマトは
イスカンダルへ行けない。
At this rate, the Yamato won't make it to Iscandar.
（ノラン）何をするつもりです？
What are you going to do?
こいつを　ぶっ潰すのよ！
Destroy this.
（徳川）非常弁　全閉鎖。
（南部）セーフティーロック　解除。
Seal all emergency vents.
Releasing safety lock. Target is in range.
（北野）標的　射界に入った。
Adjusting angle of inclination. Raising the bow slightly.
（島）
上下角　調整。　艦首　ちょい上げ。
艦体　固定！
Fix the hull!
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）総員退避！　総員退避！
Full evacuation! Full evacuation!
≫急げ～！
（ヒス）ん!?
Pressure in chamber rising. Energy charge at 120%.
（徳川）薬室内　圧力上昇！
（南部）んん…。
エネルギー充填　１２０％。
対ショック　対閃光　防御。
Prepare shock and flash defenses.
（北野）４　３　２　１。
4, 3, 2,1...
（南部）撃てぇ～!!
バシューー!!
Fire!
ドオォーーン！
（ヒス）ヤマトが　やってくれた…。
The Yamato saved us?
（ヒルデ）ヤマト？
The Yamato?
んん…。　うぅ　うっ！　あっ…。
≫ドサッ
（真田）はっ！　艦長！
Captain!
（親衛隊）６３３　軌道上で迎撃…。
（レクター）よし　分かった。→
633 engaged in orbit. Physical signal lost.
Understood.
My lord, the Desler Cannon is back on line.
総統　デスラー砲の修復が
完了したとのことです。
（タラン）あっ！
（デスラー）ふっ。
（ノラン）発射態勢に入った。
It's entering its firing sequence?
大丈夫。
（ノラン）えっ？
Don't worry.
終わったわ。
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）発射準備に入りました。
It's over.
これで　波動コアは暴走を始める。
This will force the Wave Motion Core out of control.
雪！
Yuki...
今まで　ありがとう。　これ以上→
Thank you for everything. You needn't stay with me anymore.
私に　つきあう必要はないわ。
あなたは早く…。
You should...
なぜ　そんなに
頑張ろうとするんだ？
Why are you doing all this?
Because I've finally found it.
やっと見つけたから。
あっ。
I finally understand.
やっと分かったよ。
自分にしかできないことを。
What only I can do.
自分がすべきことを！
What I must do.
それは？
It's...
君を守ることだ！
To protect you!
Fly, Zero!
飛べ　ゼロ！
（ユリーシャ）もっと速く！
Even faster! Even higher!
もっと高く！
Begin routing surplus energy to the Desler Cannon.
そんな…。
No!
Why, Norran?
どうして!?　ノラン！
分からない女だな。
あっ！
Isn't it pretty obvious?
（ノラン）これは本物のガミラス人になれる
チャンスなんだよ。→
This is my chance to be a real Garmillan.
If my lord learns that I protected this secret weapon,
僕が　この秘密兵器を守ったことを
総統が知れば→
一等ガミラスも
夢じゃないってことさ。
he may even make me a full Garmillan!
バカなこと言わないで…　うっ！
Don't be stupid!
（ノラン）バカなことじゃない！→
It isn't stupid!
だから…→
And so... This is goodbye.
あなたとは　ここでお別れです。
あっ…。
ピッピッ（スイッチ音）
うわっ！
ピッ
待って！
Wait!
ノラン！
お元気で。
Norran!
Be well.
ノラン～!!
Norran!
Farewell.
（ノラン）さようなら。
あぁ…。
（親衛隊）撃鉄システム　起動。
Firing hammer system activated.
Focus the energy so that it only strikes the Yamato.
（デスラー）出力を絞り
ピンポイントで　ヤマトを狙う。
（タラン）
総統！　もう　おやめください！→
My lord, stop! You're about to fire on your own people!
今　あなたが撃とうとしているのは
あなたの民なのですよ！
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）デスラー砲は
発射態勢に入りました。
Desler Cannon firing sequence is about to begin.
（デスラー）だからこそ　私が
この手で　やらねばならない。→
That's why I must do it myself.
偉大なるガミラスの
未来のために→
I must be the one to commit the sin
of sacrificing the noble Garmillan lives for the future of Great Garmillas.
尊い臣民の命を犠牲にする罪。
I shall live with that sin forever.
その罪は
未来永劫　私が背負っていく罪だ。
（レクター）な…　なんだ!?
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）警告　警告。→
What?
Warning... Warning... Wave Motion Core has lost control.
波動コア　制御不能。→
Wave Motion Energy has exceeded safety limits. Explosive compression imminent.
波動エネルギー　超臨界。
間もなく　爆縮します。
そうだ…　あの人の本当の名前→
Thinking about it...
I never did hear her real name...
まだ聞いてなかったな。
Jump!
（タラン）ジャンプだ！
（レクター）は…　はい！
Y-Yes, sir.
ドオォーーン！
ノラン…　あなた　うそが下手よ…。
Norran... You're a terrible liar...
All ships behind us have been destroyed! Explosion is incoming!
（乗員）後続艦は全滅！
（乗員）爆炎が接近。　接触します！
Evasive maneuvers!
（艦長）回避だ！　回避～！
なるほど　これが死か。
So... Is this how it all ends?
ドオォーーン！
Enemy fortress is collapsing.
（百合亜）
敵要塞　崩壊していきます。
What happened?
（真田）
何が起こったんだ？
あぁ…。
俺は　結局…。
In the end, I...
はっ！
I'm not dreaming, am I?
夢じゃないよね？
ああ。　夢じゃない。
No, this isn't a dream.
（２人）あっ。
Episode 23: One Man's War
Before them lies a blue planet...
A planet that will bring hope to their own home.
But no people are to be found there, save for a lonely queen.
And her words come as a surprise. She says...
Next time: The Distant Promised Land.
There are 199 days left before humanity is extinct.
２０２０年夏のオリンピック・パ
ラリンピックが
東京で開かれることに決まった。
東京への招致が決まった瞬間、